hi in this video
i want to talk about uh a follow-on
of the two videos that have uploaded on
my channel earlier
the first one was of 16 december titled
will there be a correction in january
which was uh
repeated again on my playlist on end of
december
31st december if my memory serves me
right
and the second one was an update about
natural gas in this video
i want to tell you what i think about
these two uh
uh items on my agenda
whether the markets are undergoing a
correction in the month of january
and the update on natural gas
please do subscribe to my equity master
playlist and click on the bell icon to
receive instant alerts
of future videos and in the comment
section i would love to hear
from you what you think of my videos and
what you want me to record next
book is brickbats whatever it is that
you want to give me feedback for
hey i'm looking forward to your feedback
so please
keep it going now
let me first tackle the nifty
is the market undergoing a connection
yes i think so
if you actually were to analyze what
happened in the market
according to uh dow charts or if you
want to use even candlestick charts
the signal of a reversal or having made
a peak reversal is too strong a word
here at this point in time as we stand
it's merely a correction so do remember
that the nifty has
come down after making a high of 14
600 odd and come down to 14
200 odds so we've lost only 400 odd
points
which is roughly approximately three
percent so you can't call it a very
major
reversal or a big correction either
but this kind of correction is enough to
worry
the bulls now keeping my ears to the
ground
the feedback that i received from the
market data
i i believe in trusting data as
a statistical systems trader and
behaving behavior believing in
behavioral technical analysis
i want to combine what goes on in a
trader's mind
and the traders bank balance at this
point in time
you see a three percent decline in the
nifty or 400 points
decline in the nifty would have
resulted in approximately
30 000 rupees mark to market loss
per lot all right now
in november 2020 sebi securities and
exchange board of india
has tightened the margin norms
and the penalty for non-payment of mark
to market
payments has been stepped up many fold
i think the brokers will basically cut
out
long positions of any investor trader
who does not pay margin
up front and mark to market payments
on time if you go by nse bylaws
you will realize that any client having
a mark to market
a debit which means amount payable who
does not
pay this money to the broker before the
beginning of the trading session which
is 9 00 a.m
the broker is well within his rights as
a matter of fact he is expected to not
only is it right
but it is his duty and responsibility
towards the exchange
to square up the long position of the
client
whose mark to market payments have not
yet been received
so typically what will happen is that
the traders might be very gung-ho they
are hopeful
that the market up move might start
which it might
but the point is that financial
considerations
might just throw out a lot of traders so
you see what will happen is
as per the dow theory a bear market or a
big reversal
comes only when the market surrenders 20
percent from its
recent peaks you may not get 20
20 is a far fetched cry i don't even
expect 20 percent decline to be very
honest
you will not get a 20 decline but even a
5 to 7 to 8
decline would mean that a lot of people
would have been
evicted or thrown out of their long
positions and therefore be forced to
book losses
this time around the complacency in the
people
is so great that i'm hearing stories
about how
people are so uh reckless
they feel that going long is the only
way forward you buy at 9 15 and sell out
at 3 15
if you don't get a profit wait for the
next day by next day you will definitely
get
a profit i commented on my social media
pages
about how the market might just correct
in january and i received shocking
feedback from
rookie traders who basically were not
even born
when i started trading in 1986. sir why
are you saying this the market can only
go up the markets
only go up they don't come down ever
this is shocking as somebody who's seen
three or four
major bear market collapses during my
career in the last 36 years 35 years
i find the people's attitude that
markets can go up
only one side it can only mean that they
have
over traded and now it is their
positions which is making them
talk all bull with a pun intended
i think the duress will be significantly
higher because people
are overly bridged what should you do
if you're over leveraged i think you
should bring back your positions to
manageable levels
the rule of the thumb in behavioral
technical analysis is
the only way to know if your position is
over
the size of your comfort level is if you
are
unable to get sleep in the night and you
are waiting for next morning's trading
session to open because the suspense is
killing you
it means you have over traded if you are
biting your nails rather than eating
your food at lunch time
you are over leveraged and your position
is far bigger than it should be
so cut down your exposure and
manage your position well think of a
worst case scenario where you
can afford to pay mark to market
position mark to market payments
and nurse only those kind of positions
let me now come to natural gas now i've
been talking about
my cash calendar or making a cyclical
aspect of trading in commodity markets
depending on which time of the year
we are currently at i have often said in
my videos since november december 2019
that the best way to trade natural gas
is to start
shorting it around christmas or new year
nurse those position and comes
vernal equinox in the month of march
which is the onset of summer
and you will see gas prices coming down
super sharp
and unfortunately this year the polar
vortex
the cold snap in the north pole has
basically
resulted in temperatures hitting
freezing levels in parts of north
america canada
and northern europe so gas prices went
through the roof
and human emotions being what they are
people got carried away many countries
i'm talking of countries not companies
many countries went to the spot market
and in
panic started buying natural gas
in the spot deliverable aspect
now when you buy deliveries the price
goes up
there are some deliveries which have
been transacted very small ones though
which have been transacted at 22-year
highs now to a guy who's been trading
commodity markets for donkeys years this
was shocking
this is something that we know the
prices will not sustain and
well enough on monday you are seeing a
lower circuit in the prompt month
futures of natural gas which is january
futures
it has already hit one circuit and is
trading
below that level comfortably well
so do remember that natural gas
as a commodity is so abundantly
available that the international energy
agency
is of the opinion that mankind has
approximately
300 to 400 years of forward supplies
still under the ground and we are still
making new discoveries
remember my video last year of how saudi
arabia
is developing a super super giant
gas field i'm talking of gas not oil at
jafura
it's going to spend approximately 108 to
billion dollars to develop this field
the abu dhabi
national oil company adna has discovered
a giant
belt of natural gas in the desert
in the uae so you're going to have this
gas coming into the market pretty soon
qatar one of the most prominent leading
natural gas exporters in the world
is talking about stepping up its natural
gas output
by 500 percent in the next five to ten
years
and saudi arabia which had militarily
blockaded qatar
in 2017 has now become best buddies with
qatar with prince mohammed bin salman
receiving the qatari emissary at
the gcc meeting in saudi arabia
so all's well that ends well and enemies
have now become
friends we can expect that prices will
go
the way we expect them to of course
there will be a lot of hiccups this is
not going to be smooth trading
think of it as a military exercise where
nothing goes as per
plan and variables will hit you
just when you are complicit it is said
that the
best laid plan of men and mice often go
here held a skelter when least expected
this is what has happened to natural gas
we are we are hoping that equilibrium
returns soon
on this optimistic note albeit goodbye
to you not before reminding you if you
are watching this video on youtube
please subscribe to my youtube channel
click on the bell icon and in the
comment section do let me know what you
think about this video
thank you for watching my video i have a
very very profitable day vijay bambani
signing off for now
bye-bye so do not forget to subscribe
to my free email newsletter fast profits
daily
and get my free guide how to trade
markets like a pro